[Music]
welcome back to am Northwest our next
guest shares the most interesting antique
collections and he says this one is
just glorious we welcome back antique
appraiser Gary germer great to see you
Gary thanks you for having me okay so
first of all tell us about this is a a
Native American collection of jewelry
yeah there was a an estate that we working
on and and this is just this is about
20% of her collection wow and uh I
pulled some pieces to talk about that we
going to liquidate for the estate but
she hadd been collecting for years that
and and weaving she's a textile artist
by trade and so so this was her passion
this was her real passion was was Navajo
and Native Arts so wow let's start over
here and tell me about some of the pieces
that we're seeing well mostly what we
have on the table is Navajo and
uh zouri uh jewelry they're the
ones who are really the most famous for
being silver Smiths oh and they they
started in the mid 1800s before
the 1850 1860 the native people
didn't use silver but there there was
a fellow who worked with the Mexican
blacksmiths he learned blacksmithing
first and then he learned to make the
embellishment for the Spanish because
that it was all Southwest was under
Spanish control at the time for the
horse halters and stuff and then learn
silver smithing and he was the first
one he's called they called him the old
Smith was his nickname and uh he has an
Indian name which I don't want to insult
the native people watch watching by trying
to pronounce it but um and so he then
taught his family and that's how it
started and they didn't have necessarily
their own silver so what they would
either trade with the Mexican people for
silver or they would use Mexican coins
on and they would they'd beat him down
and make it so they' make things like the
and he invented the idea of the Squash
Blossom necklace and uh we have a whole
set here which is really hard to find
and um the it was a sign wealth it was
to show your tradition and it got quickly
embraced by the people before they this
jewelry would be decorated with the
turquoise was always sacred but the uh
they would decorate with with shells
and you know bear claws and needles and
and things like that and it was once
they met with the white um uh cultures
they could also then start trading for
things like Coral that you can see added
yeah the coral and the turquoise look
stunning together right white shells
they would uh if you can see this piece
here's the white shells and they oh would
be uh they traded with Coastal tribes
for that yeah and so that's how they
got their stuff to make it and then the
designs became iconic with the um
zi and the navoo the difference
between the one of the things to look at
Zuni and Navajo Navajo people used the
the rough Stones so like this polished
of course but they'd use the whole Stones
whereas zonis used to make more things
that were more this is a whole zi set
here which I've never seen this much
in one set with a belt pins earrings
necklaces the whole thing in this they
combined a lot of the stones yeah and
they combined it into into a finer
um like this yeah there go yeah
into a finer um um designs that
they could build with it and so
uh and so if you're looking to collect
that's some of the things to look for is
you can kind of as a quick glance this
is a Zoni this is not it's just a matter
of your personal taste which one you
like better so let me ask you this
something like this when you saw this
how much when you go to settle the estate
how much would something like this
incredible necklace be worth this is an
outstanding piece uh the the the the
stones the bracelet and the earrings
all together and one of the things I need
to do to finish pricing it is that you
can find out which mine that the different
turquoises came from you can okay
yeah and so it's by the Matrix and the
color I don't know it well enough off the
top of my head that's fine okay the um
um but that a set like that is probably
in the $3,000 range wow you know3
to $4,000 wow that's amazing um
and then of course in the 70s 1970s
Ralph luren popularized it all over again
and so abolutely the Conch Shell
The Conch uh belt with the jeans
and the white linen shirt was popular
then another Trend that's happening is
I'm getting a lot of people buying bolo TI
really yeah and I I thought they kind
of went out but we sell bolo ties people
come specifically looking I must have
30 you know these are three of the nicer
ones there another little uh um Blossom
and and then a and then a hummingbird
which are also very very spiritual to
the native people yeah yeah talk to me
about the bracelet over here and then
it's all the silver necklaces that we're
seeing well this here this kind of helps
show The Matrix they call the gray spot
in there the Natural Stone and when
you're looking at turquoise it tends to be
it can be brittle so when you when
you look at it the um um usually
what you find it's been reinforced about
3% of the jewelry will be the actual
natural otherwise they put a they put
a matrix in it to or um a thing to
solidify it and then it can be polished
and it'll last longer otherwise it tends
to break um and then you don't want
to get fake but that if you saw a fake
jewelry dyed fake next to it it would
be no comparison you'd be you'd know the
difference yeah once you start looking
and so yeah and so the the the of course
there are always very very
subtle pieces here you know
yeah tell me Tell sorry tell me about
something like this this is well this is
more of a modern so you get you get the
idea of these which were their fetish
necklaces the little the little birds
and stuff were good luck charms type of a
thing and the HEI was all which is
the round discs were always uh ongoing
popular design and this is a take on
that uh and this is probably 1980s
1990s but it's a what's happening is
you'll see that the uh jewelry has evolved
you have the real traditional pieces
that are really traditional and then
there's a playoff of it so that's something
new these here are Pacific Northwest
these are the only ones here that I
could find that were Pacific Northwest so
you got like a frog and
it's inlaid with um abalone
he's decorated on all sides and Stu
incredible work it's just fun I I mean I
have the best job in the world people
give me box fulls of this and hey what is
it Gary we get to play with it amazing
we all right thank you so much Gary
appreciate it we'll put your information
on our website at k2.com we'll be right
back with more am Northwest don't go away
[Music]